I called a take-away.
我叫的外卖
A take-away.
外卖
I haven't eaten deep-fried dough sticks for a long time.
好久没吃油条了
Oh, deep-fried dough sticks are tasty.
哎呀 油条好啊
Let me try one.
先来一根
Mom, I'd like to have a talk with you.
妈妈 我跟你聊件事
About your major?
你专业的事情啊
We parents
我们呢
don't mean to meddle in this matter.
也不是说非要管
After all, what we know
毕竟我们知道的
is also limited.
东西也是有限的
We are aging.
我们呢 也老了
There are many things
很多东西呢
that we know less than you.
也没有你懂得多
How about
要不然
telling us more about
你跟我们好好地说说
the international trade major?
国贸专业
Yes.
哎
If you refuse to say something,
你要是不说的话
I will consider that you get nothing
妈妈就认为你没有办法
to refute me.
反驳
I'll say something.
我说
Go ahead.
那你说吧
I chose this major
我选国贸专业
not only because I like it
不光是因为喜欢
but I also did a lot of homework.
我也是做了很多功课的
Our major
我们专业
is more than just a little.
可不只是学些皮毛
What we are going to learn includes
我们要学的有
policies and guidelines for foreign trade,
对外经贸的政策 方针
and operating rules of the international market.
国际市场的运行规则
These things,
这些东西
if I work in the financial area,
只要是以后我搞金融
will be absolutely useful.
一定能用得上
Secondly, the employment prospect.
再说就业
Recently,
这些年来
Those foreign-related joint ventures
那些涉外合资的企业
value the graduates
很看重我们专业
from our major very much.
的毕业生的
Professional segmentation
专业细分
is becoming increasingly targeted.
也越来越有针对性了
It is true that
是
financial major is promising as well.
金融也很好
But the best may not be the fittest.
好不等于合适啊
Right? Mom
对吧 妈妈
Did you remember last time
你看你上次
the coat you adored
看中那个大衣
was only S size available?
只有S码了
Your size is XXL.
你穿XXL
You can't buy it home
你不能因为好看
just because it's pretty.
就往回买吧
Right? Dad
是吧 爸爸
You are right.
是是是
Who, who is wearing XXL size?
谁 谁穿什么XXL啦
My point is
我就是说
mom, you can't make decisions
妈妈 你不能光看网上
only from the good things online.
说的那些
After all, I
毕竟我自己
still have two years for studying.
还要再学两年呢
Hum.
嗯
Have you thought it over?
你真的想好了
Fine.
行吧
As you like.
就听你的
You, both of you
你 你们俩
won't persuade me anymore?
不劝我了
No.
不劝了
I'm telling you that
我就跟你说啊
don't come back to us crying
不要以后失败了
if you fail in the future.
哭着喊着地回来找我们
Hey.
哎哎哎
Sweetie
女儿
As long as you have faith in yourself,
只要你自己有信心
we have faith in you too.
爸爸妈妈也有信心啊
Absolutely I have, dad.
我肯定有信心啊 爸爸
Have breakfast.
吃饭 吃饭
Who is it?
谁呀
A commercial text.
营销短信
I don't think so.
我看不像
Hum.
嗯
You still know how to come back?
你还知道回来呀
What did you do last night?
昨晚干什么去了
Your dad said that he had been waiting for you.
你爸说他一直在等你
I don't know what he meant.
我也不知道什么意思
Xiaobei, Xiaobei, where is my toilet paper?
小北 小北 手纸呢
Xiaobei, haven't you come back?
小北 你还没有回来吗
When others come home,
人家回来
they help parents do housework.
都是帮着家里做家务
Look at you.
你呢
You play the smartphone or computer games
一天天的
all day long.
就知道玩手机 打游戏
You even didn't sweep the floor.
连地都不扫
I'll go out to buy groceries.
我出去买菜
Do clean the house for me.
你把家里给我打扫干净
How old are you?
多大的人了
Still so sloppy
还这么邋遢
that run outside in pajamas.
穿着睡衣就往外面跑
Change your clothes.
把衣服都给我换了啊
In the Spring Festival Day,
大过年的
you don't know
也不知道把自己
how to clean yourself up.
弄干净点
If you continue like this,
照你这样
how could you find a girlfriend?
怎么找女朋友啊
Go back as soon as your school starts.
早点开学 早点回学校
Really!
真是
Alas!
啊
Ah.
哎哟
Well,
哎
We should have eaten more.
早上就该多吃点
What if I can't enjoy a reunion dinner
你说大过年的
in the New Year's Eve?
这年夜饭
What if I can't swallow it?
我要是咽不下去
Ah.
哎呀
Well,
哎
I'm telling you that
我可跟你说啊
today is our girl's
今天可是我们闺女
first time cooking.
第一次做饭
We have to eat
就算再难吃
even if it is as inedible
我们也得吃
as slop.
就算是猪食我们也得吃
Clear?
听到没
Ah.
哎呀
Slop.
猪食
Stop eating.
别吃
Put it back.
放回去
Dad.
爸
You've cleaned for a whole day.
你说这一天就知道打扫
Sweeping and wiping
扫的擦的
are cleaner than licking.
这都比舔的干净了
Since your major matters were settled,
你专业的事解决了
your mom has taken a load off her mind.
你妈 就少了桩心事
So
这不
She is busy getting ready for the Spring Festival.
就忙着过年了
How about
要不
telling her that
你回头跟她说
you change your major again?
你又换专业得了
No.
不是
She can't leave us alone without a dinner.
那也不能不管咱们饭
What should we eat for dinner?
咱爷俩晚上吃啥呀
Just a meal. I can handle it.
不就一顿饭吗 我来
Alas.
啊
Wait for a second.
稍等一下
More dishes are to be served.
还有 还有 还有
More,
还有
more and more.
还有 还有
OK.
好了
I've made it. Come and have dinner.
结束了 快来吃饭吧
Oh.
哦
Dinner is ready.
吃饭了
Well.
哎呀
Oh yeah.
对对对
A reunion dinner made by our girl.
女儿做的年夜饭
Is it edible?
这能吃吗
Help yourself.
别客气呀
Take a seat.
坐
Oh
哦
For mom.
妈妈的
For myself.
宝宝的
Dad, give mom's chopsticks.
老爸 你给老妈分一下
All right.
好好好
Ah,
哎呀
I'm exhausted.
可把我累死了
Enjoy your meal.
来 吃
Okay.
吃
Begin to eat.
动筷子
After you.
你吃呀
I tasted them.
我刚才尝过了
They are delicious, OK?
很好吃的好不好
I'll try.
尝尝
Tasty.
好吃
Awesome.
太好吃了
Ah.
哎呀
My sweetie, they are awesome.
女儿 真是太好吃了
Well done!
你太辛苦了
Maybe this is talent.
大概这就是天赋吧
Really delicious!
真的好吃
Have a toast
来来来
to our little chef.
犒劳犒劳我们的小大厨
Happy New Year.
新年快乐
Dad
爸
Even if the dishes are inedible,
这菜就算再难吃
you can't drink all the time.
你也不能只喝酒啊
If my mom discovers
让我妈知道
that I allow you to drink secretly again,
我又纵容你偷偷喝酒
she will scold me again when she comes back.
回来又该骂我了
You can choose the major you like,
你能读自己喜欢的专业
and do whatever you like in the future.
将来做自己喜欢的事
I'm happy for you.
爸高兴
Now you are talking.
你看你这话说的
Why did you perform a show at home
那你之前还跟三叔合伙
with my uncle?
来家里演出戏
That was following your mom's order.
那是你妈的意思
From my heart, I think
我心里一直认为
you should
你就该
do whatever you like.
做自己喜欢做的事
Were you
那您这是
determined to go to a state-owned enterprise from childhood
从小立志去国企
and then your career has flourished since then?
从此风生又水起啊
Childish
幼稚
When I was playing music,
当年 我玩音乐的时候
there are countless young and beautiful ladies
不知道有多少董小姐
chasing me.
追着我跑呢
Playing music?
玩音乐
Yes.
是啊
Dad, these are just a few dishes.
爸 这才几个菜
Haven't you drunk too much?
你没喝多吧
Wait for a second.
你等着
Take a look.
看看
Oh my Gosh.
天哪
Dad,
爸
I didn't imagine that you were also
想不到你也是个
a boy with stories.
有故事的男同学啊
At that time,
那个时候啊
we formed a bank
跟几个哥们
with a few buddies.
组了一个乐队
We sang all day long tirelessly
整天风里来云里去
with no rival in my youth.
唱得那叫青春无敌呀
Your mom,
你妈
was fond of
当年就是看上我这
my uninhibited love of freedom in those years.
放纵不羁爱自由啊
Why did you go to a state-owned enterprise
那您怎么后来去国企
living a life line points?
两点一线了
Because you were born.
还不是你小子出生了呗
My age
我们那个年代
is not like yours.
哪像你们现在这样
No matter how well I play music,
音乐玩得再好
I can't earn the money for your milk powder.
也挣不来你的奶粉钱哪
Did my mom agree?
那我妈能同意吗
Your mom has always been on my side.
你妈一直很支持
At that time,
以前啊
I always thought that music
总以为音乐
was the most important thing in my life.
是我最重要的东西
But afterwards I found out that
但后来才发现
you are the most precious part in my life.
你们才是我最重要的
Happy New Year, Chubby Dango.
新年快乐啦 肉团子
What are you doing?
干嘛呢
You haven't answered my phone for so long.
这么久不接我电话
I just made a full, formal banquet
我刚刚给我们家
for two distinguished parents
两尊大佛
in my family.
做了一桌满汉全席
Well,
我说
even if auntie
就算阿姨
disagrees with your chosen major,
不同意你选择的专业
you don't have to embarrass her in this way.
你也不用这么为难她吧
What are you talking about?
谁说的
My dishes are very tasty.
我做饭可好吃了
Besides,
再说了
my mom agreed.
我妈同意我选国贸了
Really?
真的
How did you brainwash her?
你怎么给她洗脑的
Of course, it's due to your Sister Yu's
当然是凭借你鱼姐
excellent adaptability
出色的应变能力
and
还有
outstanding speaking skills
出色的那个讲解能力
and a series of non-violent measures.
一系列非暴力措施
Finally, she agreed.
然后就同意了
What about you? Is everything going well?
你呢 你那边怎么样
My parents still insist that
我爸妈还是觉得
I should choose a major related with editing.
想让我选择编辑方向
Although the final decision
虽然最后的决定权
is up to me,
在我这儿
I still need to convince them.
但我还是得说服他们
The more they are like this,
他们越是这样
the more serious I think the situation is.
我越觉得事态严重
I think you should
我觉得这事吧
make decisions by yourself.
还是得靠你自己
Well,
哎呀
I'm so torn.
我也好纠结呀
Why did you laugh? It's frightening.
你笑什么 怪瘆人的
Ah? Ah.
啊 啊
Nothing.
没事没事没事
A joke just came to my mind.
我突然想到一个笑话
A fat man
一个胖子
fell from the 20th floor.
从二十楼摔下来
What would he look like?
会变成什么样子
Chubby Dango.
肉团子呗
Goodbye. Friend.
再见 朋友
Nannan, it's time for a meal.
楠楠 出来吃饭了
OK.
嗯
Come and enjoy your meal.
来 吃吧
You ran out last night.
昨天你大晚上地跑出去
Your mother and I are very concerned.
我和你妈都很担心
From now on,
以后
You can't be so capricious.
不能这么任性了
If
如果
The start-up you mentioned.
你提那个创业的事情啊
Your mom and I
我和你妈
discussed about it.
都已经商量过了
We think
我们觉得
it is not impossible.
不是不可以实施
You mean...
你的意思是
But I must state
但是前提条件啊
the requirements clearly.
我要跟你说清楚
First of all,
第一啊
The venture capital
这个创业投资
is risky.
是有风险的
The investment return ratio
头一两年的这个
for the first two years
投资回报比呀
was a loss.
都是亏损状态
So your mother and I
所以我跟你妈呀
can only bear
只能承担你
your entrepreneurial risk for two years.
两年的创业风险
If your career hasn't improved
如果两年之内
in two years,
你还没有任何起色
we'll give it up.
我们就此作罢
Dad
爸
Secondly,
第二点呢
No matter what happens in the future,
以后不管遇到什么事情
we can discuss it nicely.
都可以好好商量
You can't just run out.
不能动不动就跑出去
Thirdly.
第三
Have dinner.
吃饭吧
Yes.
嗯
Let's eat.
来 吃饭
Eat more.
多吃点
Your dad cooked them
这是你爸呀
specially for you.
特意给你做的
Thank you, mom and dad.
谢谢爸妈
The soy sauce added
用的呀
is bought by you.
还是你买的酱油
Mom, I'm ready.
妈妈 我准备好了
Let's go.
咱走吧
Take less specialties.
你特产少拿点哦
You took too many specialties last time.
上次拿那么多
My roommates dislike them.
室友都不爱吃
Come out.
出来了
Mom.
妈妈
Your father and I
我跟你爸
will play mahjong in your third aunt's house.
去三姨家打麻将
Take a taxi to the station yourself.
你自己打车去车站吧
Take care.
路上小心
That I asked you to leave me alone
让你不管
doesn't mean you don't need to care about anything.
也不是什么都不管啊
You just gave me 100 RMB.
就给一百块钱
It costs 150 to the station.
去车站要一百五啊
Shall I get off halfway and go by myself?
我半道下来自己走啊
What a miser!
抠死
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Xiaoyu, what are you doing here?
小鱼 你怎么在这儿啊
Hello, uncle and aunt.
叔叔阿姨好
Your mom didn't see you off?
妈妈没送你啊
No. I'm taking a taxi
没有 我自己正打车
to go to the railway station myself.
打算去火车站呢
Come with us.
那我们一起走吧
We're just going to see off Nannan.
刚好我们要送楠楠
Come on. Get in the car.
快 上车
Get in the car.
上车呀
Thank you, aunt.
谢谢阿姨
Thank you, uncle.
谢谢叔叔
Nannan
楠楠啊
After arriving in the university,
你一会儿到了学校
remember to take out
记得先把被子
the quilt first.
拿出来晒晒啊
It's full of flavor after a holiday.
这一个假期啊 都是味
Recently,
还有最近这个天啊
it is still cold.
还是很冷
do remember to put on more clothes.
一定记得多穿点啊
You can't eat cold food.
冷的可不能吃
She still treats you as if you were a child.
她还是把你当小孩
Ah,
哎
Xiaoyu
小鱼啊
I heard that your mom said that
我之前听你妈妈说
you are also a member of the debate team.
你也在辩论队呀
Are you on the same debate team
是不是跟我们家楠楠
with our Nannan?
在一起呀
I...
我
I joined a debate team, too.
我 我也在辩论队
But we're not on the same team.
但我俩不是一个队的
She's on the school team.
她是校队
I'm in another team.
我 我在 我在另一个队
Oh, that's all right.
哦 这样啊
Yes.
嗯
Do you have any plan
最近实习
for your recent internship?
有什么规划吗
Aunt, I'm only a sophomore.
我 我才大二 阿姨
Ah.
哎哟
Well, your aunt's memory didn't serve well.
你看 阿姨都给忘了
Oh.
哦
Are you
那你现在应该
preparing for TEM-8?
也准备考专八了吧
It's pretty difficult to pass.
专八蛮难考的
Get ready for it.
得好好准备啊
I
我
just passed TEM-4.
四级刚过
Oh.
哦
I didn't mean it this time.
这次 可不是我故意的
They are for you.
奖励你的
That's all?
就这点啊
I went to see you
我可是穿着睡衣
all night by bus
坐了一夜大巴车
in my pajamas.
去看你的
I missed you, too.
我也想你了
Wow.
哟
I didn't expect your affection
没想到过了个年
to be stronger after the Spring Festival.
你俩更激烈了
You are more handsome.
你越来越帅了
It's for you.
送你的
Thanks.
谢了
What about mine?
那我的呢
Oh.
哦
50 yuan, thanks.
五十块钱 谢谢
Was your cola
你们家这可乐
drunk by a big star?
是大明星喝过的
Why is it so expensive?
怎么这么贵呢
Isn't your dear son's
你亲爱的儿子
cost of meals for half a month
在这儿半个月的伙食费
money?
不是钱呐
All right, you two go on.
行了 你们俩继续吧
I'll go to the back kitchen and get ready.
我去后厨准备一下
It will open soon.
马上营业了
The group sent a message.
群里发信息了
This debate perfectly explains
这辩题完美诠释了
what is the harmony of time, place and people.
什么叫天时地利人和
We are people who have experienced
都是经历过
family psychological defense war.
家庭心理防御战的人
We will surely win.
稳赢
Nan Bei
南北
I think
我想着
maybe
要不
we should be honest with others.
咱们跟大家坦白吧
Don't you also say that
你不还说
if we break up
怕咱俩万一那啥
it will be bad for the debate team?
对辩论队有什么不好吗
Did you figure it out?
想开了
The main reason is that
我主要是觉着
the bad result can hardly happen.
不太可能有万一
I'm sorry
抱歉啊
for keeping a lid on this for a long time.
瞒你们这么久
We are in love.
我们俩在一块了
Oh.
哦
What's your reaction?
你们这是什么反应啊
We didn't lie to you.
没骗你们
We are really in a relationship.
我们真的在一块了
It's true.
真的
Ah.
啊
So what?
怎么了
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Do you know that
你知道不知道
there is a feeling
有一种感觉
that
就是
you really want to get something
你很想得到一个东西
and suddenly one day
突然有一天
you finally get it,
你终于得到了它
but in your heart there will always be a sense of...
但是你心里总会有一种
I get it.
我懂我懂
emptiness?
空落落的
Ma Nan
马楠
Why don't you say something?
不说两句
Aren't you two always together?
你俩不是一直在一块吗
Who told you we've been in love?
谁跟你说一直谈恋爱了
I thought you two
我以为你俩
had been a couple.
一直是一对呢
Forget it.
拉倒吧
Sorry, I'm late.
不好意思啊 来晚了
What happened?
怎么了
Why is the atmosphere so dignified?
怎么气氛这么凝重
Nan Bei said
南北说
Xiaoyu and he are together.
他和小鱼在一起了
Oh.
哦
Ahï¼
啊
Well, what do you mean that they are together?
那个 什么叫在一起
You mean they are in love?
就是他们俩谈朋友了呗
Then how could you be so
那你们怎么还这么
calm?
这么 这么镇定
We can...
我们好了
Let's look at the files.
我们来看一下资料吧
OK?
好吧
Come on.
来吧来吧来吧
Well, we...
那个 我们下
Our rivals this time
这次的对手
are from Donggang Jiao Tong University.
是东港交通大学
They are super good. We should treat them seriously.
很厉害 大家要重视
And the competition system
而且本次比赛在赛制上
has changed a lot.
有了很大的变化
First of all, in the process of competition system,
首先是在赛制流程上
the traditional arguments, refutations and rebuttals
取消了传统的
are cancelled,
立论质询攻辩环节
and changed into two debaters vs. two debaters.
而改为了一二辩
They can choose respectively
分别进行选择
speech
申论
or refutations.
或者质询
If we choose refutations,
如果我方选择了质询
they will select
那么对方会选择
any debater
任一辩手
to accept our refutations.
接受质询
In that case, we could
那我们这样还可以
give it a try in advance
提前试试
to see what they've got.
看看他们的本事啊
You stupid boy.
你傻呀
They must
对方肯定是
send the strongest to take the move.
最强的接招啊
If so,
咱们这样
isn't it easy for us
岂不是很容易
to lose this part?
丢掉这个环节
It makes sense.
有道理
You hit the nail on the head.
说到点上了
Besides,
而且
if we choose refutations,
如果我们选择质询的话
in the three minutes of this round,
这个环节当中的三分钟
we have to share
我们就要与对手
with our opponents.
共同瓜分
and are faced with
同时还要面临对手的
the uncertainties brought by our opponents.
不确定性
So I suggest
所以我建议
that we collectively choose arguments
我们集体选择申论
and give up refutations.
放弃质询
And throughout history,
而且在历史上
few teams choose
很少有一支队伍去
refutations
选择质询
rather than arguments.
而放弃申论的
The biggest change
这次比赛还有个
in this debate
最大的改变
is the audience voting system.
这一次是观众投票制
In each round,
每个环节
audience will vote as judges.
观众都会进行投票
The voting percentage will be displayed in real time.
投票百分比会实时显示
At the end of each round,
每个环节结束的时候
the data will be locked.
锁定数据
So how can we count as winning?
那 怎么样才能算赢呢
Finally, they will calculate the total number of votes.
最后 计算总票数
Is that clear?
听懂了吗
In other words,
也就是说
No matter which team
无论哪支队伍
wins in any round of the debate
在从头到尾的比赛当中
from the beginning to the end,
任意环节都拿到了赢面
if it lags behind
最后 在观众投票中
in the audience's vote,
大比分落后
it will still lose the game.
依然会输掉比赛
If so,
那
it leaves us a lot of tactical space.
这留了很多战术空间
Exactly.
没错
However,
但是
it's not very reliable
要是把评分权给观众
to give the audience the right to score.
不太靠谱吧
This is an eternal argument.
这是一个永恒的争论
Whether the debate should
辩论到底是应该
conquer the opponent
征服对手
or the audience.
还是观众
Or neither,
或者都不说服
but pursue
而是追求
the depth of thought of the debate.
辩题的思想深度呢
But if you pursue depth,
但是如果追求深度
it will definitely be impossible
那交给观众
to leave it to the audience,
肯定就是不行的呀
because the audience's attention
因为观众的注意力
is easily get distracted,
不集中啊
which will make the debater
这会让辩手把
focus on
精力都放在
attracting the audience,
吸引观众上面
and it is difficult to have depth.
很难有深度
I think it's not that serious.
我觉得还好吧
This can
这样可以把
market the debate game.
辩论赛市场化
At least the audience would love to listen.
起码观众爱听啊
I don't have such a big pursuit.
我没那么高大上的追求
I care nothing as long as I can win.
我觉得只要能赢就行
You got it.
说得好
Comrades,
同志们
anyway,
不管怎么样
there is no choice
这场比赛对于我们来讲
for us in this competition.
都没有任何的选择余地
We must
就是让我们
dance in shackles.
戴着镣铐去跳舞
I hope everyone can do their best.
希望大家能全力以赴
The debate is a three-person system.
这场比赛是三人制的
I've already discussed with Hao.
我跟小好已经商量过了
Nan Bei, Xiaoyu and Dango,
由南北 小鱼和团子
you will be participating.
你们三个上
No, no, no.
别别别
I haven't figured out
我自己都还没搞定
how to communicate with my dad.
怎么跟我爹交流呢
Hao will be better.
小 小好姐上吧
Hao, what do you think?
小好那 要不还是你来
No problem.
好
Excellent! Enough talk.
好 废话少说
Boys and girls, let's practice.
孩儿们 咱们操练起来
The relaxed feeling
这种不用上场的
for not having to appear on the stage is so...
轻松感真的是
Welcome everyone to
欢迎大家来到
Qingguan Cup Debate Tournament,
清冠杯辩论赛
also the site of today's League
也是今天省联赛
Points Match in the provincial level.
积分赛的比赛现场
On my right is
在我右手边是
today's affirmative side,
今天的正方
the debate team from Donggang Jiaotong University,
东港交通大学辩论队
who won regional championships
他们曾连续三年
for three consecutive years.
荣获区域赛冠军
Today, their position is
今天 他们的观点是
in family relationships,
家庭关系中
being yourself is more important.
做自己更重要
Let's welcome them.
让我们欢迎他们
Tough.
好硬啊
A hard nut to crack.
难啃啊
Change another shop next time.
你下次换一家吧
It is too hard.
这个太硬了
Be grateful that I bought it for you.
给你买了就不错了
Eat it.
吃吧
The opposing side that challenged them
而挑战他们的反方
was the debate team 235,
则是在一连串比赛中
a dark horse
大放异彩
that flourished
异军突起的
in a series of games.
二三五辩论队
Let's give them
也让我们把掌声
applause, too.
送给他们
In this competition,
本次比赛
we adopt the new system
采用二零二零工业杯
of the 2020 Industrial Cup.
新番赛制
Don't worry. I'll watch your back.
放心 我罩着你
Be in command of yourself.
你快自己控制住吧
Don't cause troubles.
你别捅娄子就行
The result of this competition
本次比赛的结果
is decided by the on-site audience
由现场观众
voting together.
共同投票决定
Each audience can change votes for three times.
每位观众可改投三次
Please
请各位观众
use your rights carefully
谨慎使用手中的权利
and make responsible choices.
做出负责的选择
Now I declare
现在我宣布
the competition officially started.
本场比赛正式开始
Now let's invite the first positive speaker
下面有请正方一辩
to speak first.
首先发言
Do you prefer a speech or a refutation?
请问选择申论还是质询
We choose speech.
申论
As expected.
不出所料
Let's welcome them to state arguments.
有请正方一辩进行申论
Thank you, chairman.
谢谢主席
Greetings to all of you present,
问候在场各位
firstly, I'd like to ask a question to everyone.
首先请问大家一个问题
In our country,
在我国
How many family relationships
一个包含爷爷奶奶
do we have
外公外婆
including grandparents,
父母兄妹在内的
parents,
基本八口之家
brothers or sisters?
拥有几种家庭关系
I am my parents' daughter,
我是我爸妈的女儿
my paternal grandfather's granddaughter,
我是我爷爷的孙女
my maternal grandfather's granddaughter,
我是我外公的外孙女
my younger brother's elder sister,
我又是弟弟的姐姐
my father is also my grandfather's
我爸爸又是我爷爷
son,
的儿子
my mother's husband,
妈妈的丈夫
and my maternal grandmother's son-in-law.
我外婆的女婿
And
然后
Actually,
其实呢
one equation
有一个家庭关系数的
for the number of family relationships
方程式
is that the number of family relationships
是家庭关系数
equals the total number of people minus one divided by two.
等于总人数减一除以二
In this way,
这样算来
in an ordinary family,
一个普通的家庭中
there are 28
就有二十八种
different family relationships.
不同的家庭关系
You are a father
你是爸爸的同时
also a son, a husband and a son-in-law.
也是儿子 丈夫 女婿
You are a son,
你是儿子的同时
also an elder or younger brother,
也是哥哥或弟弟
a paternal or maternal grandson.
孙子或外孙
Do you know why
我们之所以在如此
in such a complicated family relationship
纷繁复杂的家庭关系中
we still feel comfortable
依然还觉得游刃有余
and don't seem
似乎也没有焦头烂额嘛
to be in trouble?
您知道这是因为什么吗
It's because
这就是因为
behind all decisions
所有决策的背后
is yourself.
都是你自己
You just have to be yourself
你只要做好你自己
and being yourself
而做好自己在我们看来
is the cornerstone
就是一切
of all healthy relationships in our view.
健康关系的基石
It is not easy
做好自己
to be yourself
做好扮演着二十八个
and play
不同角色的自己
28 different roles.
已属不易
Throughout the history,
纵观古往今来
killing brother or father, betrayed by relatives.
杀兄弑父 众叛亲离
Which family tragedy
哪一出家庭悲剧的产生
was not caused by
不是因为
the dislocation
家庭身份的错位
or lack of family identity?
或缺失造成的
Do you think I would
你以为我愿意
be drunk every day?
每天都喝得烂醉如泥吗
Isn't it for the family?
我还不是为了这个家
Do you think
你以为
I'm still willing to be with you?
我还愿意跟你在一起吗
It's for the family.
我还不是为了这个家
The sentence "It's for
一句我还不是为了
this family"
这个家
using moral kidnapping
用道德绑架
has pushed many family relationships
将多少家庭关系
to pieces
推向了支离破碎
and total collapse.
分崩离析
On the other hand, those happy families
反观那些幸福的家庭
who have kind fathers and filial sons with good brotherhood,
父慈子孝 兄恭弟友
which one can realize
哪一个不是因为
the unity and harmony of the family
做好了自己的分内之事
without
才能够实现家庭
fulfilling their own duties?
的团结和睦呢
I hope that we will put aside
希望我们放下
the pretense that it's for the family.
为了家人的幌子
Instead, shoulder family responsibilities,
扛起家庭责任
and be ourselves.
做好自己的大旗
Stop
不要再
hurting the family in the name of love.
以爱之名伤害家庭
Thank you.
谢谢
What the hell? What's her routine?
我去 这姐们什么路子
I know she must be wrong
我知道她说得肯定不对
but I can't figure out
但我听不出来
what's wrong.
什么问题啊
Calm down. It's a piece of cake.
淡定点 小场面
Hao, defeat her.
小好姐 击败她
Now
下面
let's give the floor to the first negative speaker.
有请反方一辩发言
Do you prefer
请问您选择
a speech or a refutation?
申论还是质询
Speech.
申论
Please.
有请
Thanks, chairman.
谢谢主席
Hello, everyone.
大家好
Just now my fellow debater argued that
刚刚对方辩友说
the family relationship was too complicated
家庭关系太复杂了
for me to cope with,
我应付不来
so I had to be myself.
所以我只能做好自己
The argument given by her
对方给出的论据
is called the number of family relations.
叫家庭关系数
The formula is simple and clear,
公式简洁明了
but the number
但是数字
has neither temperature
既没有温度
nor meaning.
也没有意义
Of course, I can't be
我当然不能做
grandpa's daughter.
爷爷的女儿
Neither can I be father's wife.
也做不了爸爸的妻子
But can't I take care of them
但我不能替
for grandpa and dad?
爷爷爸爸照顾他们吗
Empathy is not a substitute.
感同身受不是取代
Putting yourself in the position is not a copy.
设身处地更不是复制吧
Are family relationships
家庭关系
really that complicated?
真的有那么复杂吗
Your mother gave birth to you
母亲为了你
after 10 months.
怀胎十月 一朝分娩
Your father
父亲为了你
worked hard for you and even quit smoking and drinking.
戒烟戒酒 努力工作
What I actually see is
我看到的分明是
simple and straightforward love.
简单直白的爱
What's so complicated about it?
它到底复杂在哪儿
Even as my fellow debater said that
即使就如对方辩友所说
you have 28 family relationships,
你有二十八种家庭关系
isn't it
那这何尝又不是
28 love?
二十八份爱呢
Throughout the ages,
古往今来
whoever kills brothers and fathers
杀兄弑父者
is not a lonely person?
哪个不是孤家寡人
Whoever is betrayed by their relatives
众叛亲离者
is not
哪个又不是
for their own self-interest?
为了一己私利
So where is
那么问题
the problem?
到底出现在哪儿
Our team believes that
我方认为
it's precisely because
恰恰就是因为
they are too concerned
他们都太顾着
about being themselves.
做好自己了
My fellow debater said
对方辩友说
Families who consist of kind fathers and filial sons with good brotherhood
父慈子孝 兄恭弟友
are a model of family harmony.
是家庭和谐的典范
But the correct reading should be
但正确的读法应该是
that father is kind to son and son is filial to father
父慈子 子孝父
with brothers love and respect each other.
兄恭弟 弟友兄吧
Fathers care for children.
父亲为了孩子
Children care about their father.
孩子为了父亲
Older brothers care for younger brothers
哥哥为了弟弟
and the vice versa.
弟弟为了哥哥
This is the family we desire,
这才是我们想要的家
isn't it?
不是吗
The crow feeds parents. The lamb kneels down to suckle.
乌鸦反哺 羊羔跪乳
This is the truth
这是自然界
that all things in nature know.
万物都通晓的道理
Family affection makes altruism,
亲情让看上去
which seems not in line
不符合
with natural selection
物竞天择的利他性
become
变成了
the most powerful link
牢牢维系家庭关系的
to firmly maintain family relations.
最有力纽带
We believe that in family relations,
我方认为 在家庭关系中
being a family member is more important than being yourself.
为家人比做自己更重要
Because only when you think of them
因为只有你发自内心地
and act for them from your heart,
为了他们 想着他们
can we be called a family.
我们才可以叫作一家人
Thank you.
谢谢
Fight fire with fire.
以彼之道还施彼身
Speech combined with the rhetorical question.
反问当中还能做申论
How awesome Hao is!
还得是小好啊
I didn't expect
真没想到
Hao to be able to take advantage of emotions.
小好姐也能打情绪流
I almost gave my heart to her.
我这心都快化了
She did move the audience.
场面确实很精彩
But the rational argument of the speech
但是为了场面优势
was sacrificed for the real-time audience.
牺牲了申论的理性辩述
What are you afraid of?
怕什么
There are no professional judges in this competition.
这场又没有评委
My fellow debater said that
对方辩友说
for the family is a kind of altruism.
为家人是一种利他性
Must altruism be good
在家庭关系中利他性
in family relationships?
一定是好的吗
Not necessarily.
未必见得
Everyone has read
大家都读过
The Gift of the Magi.
《欧亨利的礼物》
The husband sold his watch
丈夫为了给妻子买梳子
to buy a comb for his wife.
而卖掉了手表
The wife cut her hair
妻子为了给丈夫买表带
to buy a watchband for her husband.
而剪掉了头发
This is certainly
这固然是
a beautiful relationship.
一段美好的感情
But is it because of the beauty
可是让它
of this relationship
成为不朽名篇的
that makes it
究竟是
an immortal masterpiece?
因为这段感情的美好吗
No.
不是
It's because of
而是因为
the bitterness of this relationship.
这段感情的苦涩
The root of the bitterness
这段关系
of this relationship
苦涩的根源在于
is that they both forgot that
两个人都忘掉了
being themselves
做自己
is the cornerstone of a relationship.
才是一段感情的基石
The relationship between our people
我们人与人之间的关系
is like a line between two points.
就像两点之间的线
Is it necessary
是不是首先要有
to have my point first
我这个点
so that this line can be connected?
这个线才能连得起来呢
If all of us are like
如果我们大家都像
this couple
这对夫妻一样
and lose our points,
丧失了自我的这个点
what we end up with
我们最后得到的
is a comb without hair
只能是失去头发的梳子
or a strap without a watch.
和没有手表的表带
We always say it's for your own good.
我们都说为你好为你好
But in most cases,
常常是
we do things from our point of view.
我们以为的为你好
We often
我们经常因为
cook a dish
孩子的一句
just because of the child's comment
哎呀真好吃
"Oh, it's so delicious"
我们就做一道菜
to keep cooking the same dish.
一直做
I like
因为我喜欢
James Cameron.
詹姆斯·卡梅隆
My girlfriend
我的女朋友
saved up living expenses
就攒着生活费
to buy me the Collector's Edition of Terminator,
给我买终结者的典藏版
but what I like
但是我喜欢的是
is Avatar.
阿凡达呀
Then the worst thing is that
那么最惨的是
I have to watch the Terminator
我还得陪着她一块
with her.
看终结者
So everybody,
所以说 各位
why don't we admit that
我们为什么不能承认
no one can fully understand
没有人能够完全地了解
another person?
另外一个人呢
Even if you are his wife,
哪怕你是他的妻子
husband, parents or children,
丈夫 父母 儿女
you can't.
都不可能
So if we can't,
那么既然不能
why can't we
我们为什么不能
be ourselves?
做好我们自己呢
There are not many major disputes
家庭关系中
in the family relationship,
没有多少大是大非
but trivial matters
都是锅勺
that the spoon
难免不碰锅沿的
will definitely touch the edge of the pot.
鸡毛蒜皮
Be yourself.
做好自己
Fully express your demands.
充分表达自我诉求
Keep the diversity in family relations.
让家庭关系中的多样性
Seek common ground while reserving differences.
保持求同存异
So that these problems and contradictions
那这些问题和矛盾
will not make a big mistake
才不会因为不好说
because they are hard
不敢做
to say and dare not do.
而积重难返 铸就大错
Do we have to sacrifice
难道非得让我们牺牲
our most precious things
我们自己最宝贵的东西
for an unwanted gift
换取对方一个
from each other?
不需要的礼物吗
Don't do that.
不要这样
It's more important to be yourself. Thank you.
做自己更重要 谢谢
The competition is a bit fierce.
战况有点激烈
Oh, crumbs! The speech prepared by Xiaoyu
糟了 小鱼准备的申论
is completely inconsistent with his point of view.
跟他的观点完全不合呀
Next is the time for
接下来是反方二辩的
the second negative speaker.
发言时间
Will the second negative speaker
请问反方二辩
choose speech or refutations?
采取申论还是质询
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Will the second negative speaker...
请问反方二辩
I choose refutations.
我选质询
Why is it different from what was agreed?
怎么跟说好的不一样啊
You have only three minutes in this part.
环节时间只有三分钟
The effect of refutations
质询效果
is certainly not as good as that of speeches.
肯定比不上申论
What the hell is she thinking?
小鱼到底在想什么呀
Trust her. She knows what she is doing.
相信她 她有数
You know nothing. Stop eating.
有数什么有数 你别吃了
Now let's welcome
那么下面就有请
the second negative speaker
反方二辩
to question
对正方任意辩手
any positive speaker.
进行质询
Time is three minutes.
时间为三分钟
Hello, my fellow debater.
对方辩友 您好
Hello.
您好
You just said that
您刚才说
because everyone is different,
因为每个人都是不同的
we have no clue about
所以我们根本不知道
what is really good for others.
什么对别人是真的好
Is that true?
对吗
Yes.
是
But shouldn't my family be
可是家人不应该是
the one who knows me best?
最了解我的人吗
My favorite food is
我最爱吃
my mother's egg fried rice.
妈妈做的蛋炒饭
She knows that.
这她知道啊
Why do you have to say
为什么您非要
she doesn't know?
说她不知道呢
How does your mother know
您妈妈知道
you love egg fried rice?
你爱吃蛋炒饭
Is it because you
是不是首先因为你
chose to be yourself
做了自己
and expressed your affection
表达出来你的喜爱
so that she could know?
她才能知道的呢
So in your definition,
所以在您方的定义中
being yourself is to be honest.
只要真诚就是做自己
Acting for the family must be
为家人一定就是
insincerity?
虚情假意喽
It's not what I mean.
不是这个意思
My point is that
我是说
it is a more authentic choice
当做自己和为家人
to be yourself
产生冲突的时候
when there is conflict between you and your family.
做自己是更真实的选择
My father likes chicken legs very much.
我爸特别爱吃鸡腿
But he always
可是他每次都
chooses to give them to me.
选择让给我吃
Is this for himself
请问这是他做自己
or for me?
还是为了我呢
It's for you.
是为了你呀
That's why he lost...
所以说他丧失了
But isn't the choice from
可这难道不是出自
his true heart?
他真实的内心吗
Is his choice
他的选择难道是
hypocritical?
虚情假意的吗
Let's take a step back.
我们退一步讲
My fellow debater, you're right.
对方辩友 您说得对
But I'm afraid many more important things
可是很多更重要的事情
are not as simple
恐怕没有您
as you think.
想象得这么简单
For example, to be pushed to get married.
比如说催婚
Should I be faithful to myself
我是要忠于自己的选择
or rush to close life events
还是为了父母的安心
for the peace
去匆忙地了结
of my parents?
人生大事呢
Under this competition system,
这个赛制下
rhetorical questioning is not foul.
质询反问不犯规
They want to use rhetorical questions to control the tempo.
他们想用反问带动节奏
Xiaoyu won't bite.
小鱼不会上当的
She'll ask back.
她会反问回去的
Why do parents push you to get married?
父母为什么会催婚
Maybe because your parents
可能是您的父母
are eager to hold a grandson.
着急抱孙子呗
You mean being urged to give birth to a baby.
您那是催生吧
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
you are so naive.
那你就太年轻了
They are like peas and carrots.
结婚生子这是一个词语
Just two steps.
分两步走而已嘛
Getting married and having children is a joy in life.
结婚生子人生乐事
Parents hope you will be happy as soon as possible.
父母希望你早日幸福
Is that wrong?
有什么不对
Parents want me
父母希望我
to be happy so they urge me to get married.
幸福所以说催婚
But this
但是催婚
becomes the most unfortunate thing
就变成我人生当中
in my life.
最不幸的事
My fellow debater, in my opinion,
对方辩友 在我看来
it perfectly explains
这完美地诠释
why it's better to be yourself for others.
为他人不如做自己嘛
This guy has really got something.
这家伙还是有点东西
Where is the key to the problem?
催婚问题的关键在哪里
Is it caused by your parents
是父母为你着想
for your sake?
造成的吗
They just want
他们不过是希望
you to have hot meal to eat
远在异乡的你
clean clothes to wear
有口热饭吃
and someone to take care of you
有干净的衣服穿
when you are sick.
生病了有个人能照顾你
Is that a problem?
这又有什么问题
But you don't want to get married.
可是您不想结婚
That's the problem.
这不就出现问题了吗
So as long as there are different views,
所以只要观点不同
there will be problems, right?
就一定会有问题 对吗
Isn't it a fact?
难道不是吗
So the state of harmony but difference
那和而不同的状态
does not exist?
是不存在的喽
Harmony but different
和而不同
is of course the most ideal state.
当然是最理想的状态
But don't the problems arise in the family relationship
可是家庭关系中
when people in a family
不就是因为家庭之间
hold different views?
家人的观点不同吗
No.
不是
The difference is not terrible.
不同不可怕
the terrible thing is the inability
可怕的是无法
to understand the differences in family members.
理解家人的不同
It is due to incomprehension
因为无法理解
that the family relationship
而导致家庭关系
has problems.
出现问题
Is it the most important thing
此时做自己
to be yourself at this time?
还是最重要的吗
Even so,
即便如此
isn't it more important
做自己作为一切
to be yourself
健康关系的基石
as the cornerstone of all healthy relationships?
不是更重要吗
The importance of the foundation
基础的重要性
was just refuted
我方一辩
by the first speaker on our side.
刚刚已经反驳过了
What is your more important
请问您方更重要的
criterion for judgment?
判断标准是什么
It's the foundation.
就是基础性
What is
请问
your standard?
您方的标准是什么呢
Being yourself or for the family
做自己和为家人
which is more conducive to problem-solving,
哪个更有利于解决问题
is more important.
哪个就更重要
Therefore, my fellow debater,
所以说对方辩友
it is more conducive
做自己
to solve the problem by being yourself.
更有利于解决问题
Acting for the family
您方为家人
is called evasion problem.
那叫逃避问题啊
Very good.
非常好
So, my fellow debater,
所以对方辩友
do you agree with
您是认同
our criterion for judgment?
我方的判断标准了吗
Thank you.
谢谢对方辩友
We did not win this round.
这一轮又没有拿下来啊
I thought there would be no problem.
我还以为没问题呢
Relax.
没事
Although we suffered
虽然这一轮
a small loss in this round,
我们吃了小亏
we took a big advantage.
但占了大便宜
Although it was a small win on the scene,
虽然场面上小赢
it was more difficult
但是被对方占掉了
because the opponent had taken over
判断标准和比较共识
the judgment standard and comparative consensus.
这就比较难办了
We have set standards
能在这轮质询
on this round of refutation,
上确立标准
giving us more confident
整个自由辩论
in the free debate.
就更有把握了
And the result of the debate
而且比赛的结果是
is calculated by
所有的环节
adding the votes of all rounds.
票数相加计算的
The victory or defeat of a single round is not vital.
单场的胜负没那么重要
So the final result
那接下来的胜负就看
depends on the free debate.
就看自由辩论了
If the other party abandons the essential discussion
如果对方放弃本质探讨
and only talks about the methodology
只聊解决家庭问题
of solving family problems,
的方法论
it will only make us
只会让我们
lose more battlefields.
失去更多的战场
We must turn the table around.
必须拉回来
Make use of the existing advantages
利用现有的优势
to seize the battlefield of methodology
抓住方法论的战场
and destroy their arguments.
打掉他们的立论
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Now, it's the time for
接下来是本场比赛的
the free debate.
自由辩论环节
The two sides speak alternately,
双方交替发言
four minutes for each side.
每方时间各四分钟
Start from the affirmative side, please.
从正方先开始 有请
If you have a
如果你有一个
domestic violence husband,
家暴的丈夫
should you stand up bravely
请问你是应该勇敢地
and be yourself,
站出来做自己
or not resist
还是为了所谓的和气
for the so-called harmony?
不予反抗呢
Everyone, remember
各位记住
that when you encounter domestic violence,
遇到家暴
call the police, get divorced
报警离婚分财产
and divide your property.
一波流程走起
This wave of processes
这才是对你
is the biggest responsibility for you and your family.
和娘家人的最大负责
On the contrary, doesn't this husband's
反倒是这位丈夫的
domestic violence
家暴行为
justify the horror of being only for himself
不正说明了只为自己
and not for his family?
不为家人的可怕吗
If a person's personality is irritable
如果一个人的性格暴躁
and stubborn,
顽劣不堪
would you still think that
你还会认为这样的人
being himself
做自己
is good for family relations?
有利于家庭关系吗
According to what you said,
按照您的说法
is it better for family relations
是不是如果他天性温良
if he has a gentle nature
做自己
to be himself?
对家庭关系就更好了呢
Are there more good people
那到底是好人多
or more bad people?
还是坏人多呢
Are you questioning being yourself
您方是质疑做自己
or discriminating against character defects?
还是歧视性格缺陷呢
For the phenomenon of people who help brothers at no cost,
扶弟魔这种现象
is it a disadvantage for the family?
算不算为家人的弊端呢
It is originated from
扶弟魔的产生于
a deformed
一种畸形的
family relationship and cognition.
家庭关系与认知
Don't evade problems.
对方辩友不要逃避嘛
Please answer me directly.
请直接回答我
Does it count as a disadvantage?
算不算为家人的弊端
I don't think so.
我觉得不算
Why?
怎么不算
How can the women who are known as
每一个被叫作
helping brothers at no cost
扶弟魔的女人
betraying
都在背叛
her and her husband's small family
自己与丈夫的小家
be regarded as family members?
又怎么能算是为家人呢
Xiaoyu is really good at jumping out of the circle.
小鱼是真的爱跳逻辑
Because she is unreasonable.
因为她不讲道理呀
The phenomenon
扶弟魔现象的出现
is due to the abnormal values
是因为长期的家庭环境
caused by long-term family environment
和家庭教育
and family education,
导致的畸形价值观
rather than simply being yourself,
而非单纯的做自己
or the choice made for the family.
还是为家人的选择问题
Essentially,
说到底
son preference
重男轻女
is the culprit.
才是扶弟魔的元凶
In 2013,
二零一三年
An old father in Jiangxi
江西的一位老父亲
tightened his belt and bled himself white
为了给自己的儿子
in order to marry a daughter-in-law
娶个媳妇
for his son.
省吃俭用被榨干
As a result, he
结果还遭受到了
was abused by his son.
儿子的虐待
If he was willing to be himself,
如果他肯做自己的话
would such a tragedy
是不是这样的悲剧
not happen?
就不会发生了呢
It is human nature
为儿女考虑
to consider for children.
乃是人之常情
You don't blame
你不去指责那个
the greedy son,
贪得无厌的儿子
but blame
却去指责一个
a father who worked hard for the child.
为孩子掏尽心血的父亲
Won't your heart hurt?
您心不会痛吗
Is it a kind of compromise and tolerance
为家人是不是一种
to do things for the family?
对家人的妥协和包容呢
Wrong.
不对
Acting for the family is an attitude,
为家人是种心态
not necessarily
而不一定是
a very specific behavior.
非常具体的行为
So your side
所以对方辩友的
just think about the family
观点就是
from your heart.
为家人心里想想就好
What you behave
身体却是
is very honest to be yourself.
很诚实地做自己喽
They are in a standoff.
双方纠缠不下
Almost at the same level.
场面上分不出来
It's good for us.
那对我们是好事
Our emphasis on acting for the family
我方强调的为家人是
is a way
感同身受
to empathize and promote
从而促进交流
communication and exchanges.
与沟通的一种方式
An old couple,
一对老夫妻
the husband likes to eat fish head
丈夫喜欢吃鱼头
and the wife likes to eat fish tail.
妻子喜欢吃鱼尾
They both give
为了彼此
each other
他们都把自己
their favorite part
喜欢的那部分
for each other.
给对方吃
As a result, no one can eat
结果谁都没能吃到
the part they like.
自己喜欢的那部分
They do things for the family.
为家人
Why didn't they promote communication?
为什么没有促进沟通
Instead, they wasted each other's hearts
反而在沉默中
in silence.
消耗了彼此的心意呢
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
This is a love story.
这是一个爱情故事啊
Don't you think it's warm?
你不觉得很暖心吗
If they only care about
如果他们都只顾着
themselves,
做自己的话
will such
那这样
a touching love story
感人至深的爱情故事
still exist?
是不是就不存在了呢
There are also many love stories,
爱情故事同样还有很多
all of which can be deeply moving.
都可以感人至深
But if blind dedication
但是如果把盲目奉献
is advertised as a love story,
标榜成爱情故事的话
is it the biggest misunderstanding
是不是对真爱
of true love?
最大的误解呢
Do you mean
您是说
to exchange a lifetime love
用一辈子不吃鱼头
by not eating fish head for a lifetime?
来换一份一生挚爱吗
Yes, I do.
我愿意呀
After all, true love is hard to get.
毕竟真爱难得
Although I can't eat fish head,
我不吃鱼头
I can still eat
还可以吃
hot pot, barbecue, ice cream,
火锅 烧烤 冰淇淋
right?
不是吗
I do, too.
我也愿意
Is this a public display of affection?
这是在秀恩爱吗
You will get used to it.
习惯就好
I'm in my 30s.
我都三十了
Ten years ago, my dad didn't let me buy Bitcoin
十年前我爸为了我好
for my own sake.
死活不让我买比特币
He insisted that they were all liars,
非说都是骗子
so financial freedom
于是财务自由
passed me by.
与我擦肩而过
Why did you harm your family
怎么为了家人
for the sake of your family?
反而害了家人呢
It happened that ten years ago,
恰好在十年前
when I was in middle school,
我在中学的时候也要
I wanted to start a business and open a shop.
创业开店
I didn't listen to anyone who tried to persuade me
谁劝我都不听
and I lost everything.
结果赔得血本无归
Why is it so miserable
为什么做自己
to be yourself?
也会这么惨呢
If you don't be yourself first,
如果不先做自己
I eat whatever you prepared
你问我想吃什么都行
and do whatever you like.
我想要什么都行
In the seemingly peaceful situation,
看似和平的状况
my family members can't hear my heartfelt wishes.
家人却听不到我的心声
How can they be
如何才能
truly good for me?
真正地为我好呢
I think you can
我觉得您可以
be yourself first.
先做好自己
So being yourself
所以做自己
is a prerequisite for your family,
是为家人的前提
right?
对吗
Is the prerequisite more important?
前提就等于更重要吗
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
don't you remember
您不记得
the criterion
我们刚刚确认过的
we just confirmed?
判断标准了吗
I feel like Xiaoyu
感觉小鱼
was pushed back to the standard line again.
又被逼回标准线了
Almost. Keep on attacking.
还差点 继续攻
We need to find a breakthrough.
要找到一个突破点
to pull the topic back
把辩题从场面上拉回
to the core issue.
核心议题
Mommy's boys
妈宝男
think about moms' feelings all the time.
处处考虑妈妈的感受
Are they good men?
算不算好男人呢
I think mommy's boys
我觉得妈宝男
are not thinking about moms.
不是处处考虑妈妈
They just believe
他是觉得
what their moms said is right.
他妈妈说得都对
Their moms, it's impossible for their moms
他妈 他妈不可能
to be right all the time.
什么都对呀
He thinks his mother is always right.
他觉得他妈都对
Isn't that a problem?
这难道不是问题吗
Yes, it is.
是问题啊
So I have never agreed
所以我从来没有认同过
behaviors of mommy's boys are right.
妈宝男就是正确的呀
On the contrary, let sons
相反的是让自己的儿子
live the way they like.
活成自己喜欢的样子
Is this for their sons?
这是为了儿子吗
This is simply satisfying themselves.
这是单纯地满足自己
Don't worry. I'm not.
放心啊 我不是
Scram!
滚
I wanted to apply for literature
大学报志愿
in a college application form.
我想学文学
But my parents asked me to study finance.
而父母让我学金融
Should I give up my dream
我该不该为了父母
for the sake of my parents?
而放弃自己的梦想呢
In that case,
这个时候
your parents should
您的父母应该
respect your wishes.
尊重您的意愿
Be more considerate of your family.
多为家人着想
The more you communicate, the better you understand.
多沟通多理解嘛
When family members conflict with
当家人与自己的意愿
their own wishes,
发生冲突时
if you act for the family,
如果为家人更重要
shouldn't you follow
不应该遵循
the family's wishes?
家人的意愿吗
Not necessarily.
不一定啊
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
this is not necessarily.
这也不一定
That is not necessarily.
那也不一定
What is more important?
那什么才叫更重要呢
In this example,
在这个例子中
whether it is you or your parents,
不论是你还是父母
if you think more about your family,
多为家人想一想
conflicts will not arise.
矛盾就不会产生
Similarly, whether it is you or your parents,
同样 不论是你还是父母
conflicts are inevitable
如果大家都只顾着
if everyone is just about to
做自己的话
be themselves.
矛盾就不可避免
Doesn't this suggest that
这不就正说明着
it is more important to act for your family?
为家人更重要吗
On the other hand,
反过来说
does a good family relationship
一个良好的家庭关系
have fewer conflicts, the better?
是不是矛盾越少越好呢
Does avoiding conflict
避免矛盾
necessarily benefit family relationships?
一定有利于家庭关系吗
Sometimes bickering
有时候斗斗嘴
is also a kind of
也不失为一种
family fun.
家庭情趣嘛
So more conflicts
所以矛盾多了
is
反而是
a sign of good family relations?
良好家庭关系的标志了
Well done!
漂亮
When the weather gets cold,
天凉了
should I wear thermals
我要不要为了我妈
for my mother?
而穿秋裤
Does it count as a family relationship?
穿秋裤算家庭关系吗
Doesn't it count?
不算吗
Fine, it does.
好吧 算
Wearing thermals is a way for your mother
穿秋裤是妈妈
to express her concern for you.
对你表达关心的方式
But you just went against your parents
可你偏偏为了做自己
in order to be yourself,
而去顶撞父母
wasting the kindness.
辜负了好心
Treat concern as a contradiction.
把关心当成矛盾
A good family relationship
好好的家庭关系
has become a total mess.
就变成鸡飞狗跳的闹剧
Don't you think it a pity?
你不会觉得很可惜吗
Whenever we list
但凡我方列举出
the drawbacks of acting for the family,
为家人的各种弊端
they will say that
对方就说这是
it is an unhealthy family relationship,
不健康的家庭关系
instead of the family's fault.
而不是为家人的错
So I would like to ask
那么我想请问对方辩友
how to define acting for the family?
到底什么才是为家人呢
That's it.
就是这个
I think they should be compromise and tolerance.
我认为是 妥协和包容
What is the essence
那 做自己的
of being yourself?
本质又是什么呢
Principles and persistence.
原则和坚持
Therefore, what we really need
因此我们今天
to discuss today
真正要讨论的
is based on the following two consensus.
正是基于以下两点共识
In an intimate relationship
在类似家庭这样的
like a family,
亲密关系中
which one is more important,
妥协和坚持
compromise or persistence?
到底哪个更重要
Right?
对吗
I think you are right.
我觉得您说得没错
He admitted it.
认了
Don't worry. He knows what he is doing.
没事 南北心里有数
Next
接下来
is the final round
是本场比赛的
of this competition.
最后一个环节
Summary statement.
总结陈词
Three and a half minutes for each team.
双方时间各三分半
Start from the negative side, please.
从反方先开始 有请
Thank you, chairman.
谢谢主席
Hello, everyone.
大家好
I think the affirmative side
我觉得对方辩友
is right.
说得没错
The topic we are discussing today
我们今天讨论的辩题
is to discuss
就是讨论在
which one is more important
家庭的亲密关系中
in the close relationship like a family,
妥协和坚持
compromise or persistence?
到底哪一个更重要
But we don't seem to
但我们似乎好像没有
figure out one issue.
想明白一个问题
What are we compromising?
我们妥协的是什么
And what are we insisting on?
坚持的又是什么
My fellow debater would definitely say
对方辩友当然会说
we insist on being ourselves.
我们坚持的是自我
We insist on independence
是独立
and that our personalities are not disturbed.
是人格不被干扰
However,
但是
does our family relationship
当我们在外出
really get better
求学的时候
when we go out
我们的家庭关系
to study?
真的就变好了吗
Think it over,
仔细想一想
who called to whom
我们上一次和父母通话
the last time we talked to our parents?
到底是谁打给谁的
The most chat records with our parents,
我们和父母的聊天记录
are they
最多的
transfer records?
到底是不是转账记录呢
We talk increasingly less
我们和父母的话
with our parents.
越来越少
The parents have also turned
父母也曾将
the most irresistible order
最不可违抗的命令
into
变成现在
a cautious inquiry.
小心翼翼的询问
Is this really what we want?
这真的是我们想要的吗
No.
不
It shouldn't be.
不应该是
Haven't our parents
我们的父母
been young?
难道没有年轻过吗
been youthful?
难道没有过青春吗
They also got a perm,
他们曾经也烫着头
wearing flared trousers
穿着喇叭裤
carried with radios
扛着收音机
dreaming to be a singer
想变成一个歌手
to form a bank
想组成一个乐队
and to realize their dreams.
想完成自己的梦想
What made them wear shirts
是什么让他们理了平头
with cropped hairs
穿上衬衫
living a life line points day after day?
日复一日地两点一线
It's me.
是我
It's us.
是我们
It's every family member.
是每一个家人
Once after he was drunk
有一次我在我爸
I asked
喝醉酒之后
my dad
我问他
do you regret
为了我
giving up your dream
放弃你自己的梦想
for me?
你后悔吗
At that time,
以前啊
I always thought that music
总以为音乐
was the most important thing in my life.
是我最重要的东西
But afterwards I found out that
但后来才发现
you are the most precious part in my life.
你们才是我最重要的
So
所以呀
I shaved my hair,
我就剃掉头发
sold the guitar
卖掉吉他
and make money for your milk powder.
给你去挣奶粉钱去了
Dad
爸
Do you regret it?
那您后悔吗
Do you regret
你做我的儿子
being my son?
你后悔吗
He smiled and asked me back.
他笑着反问我说
Do you regret being my son?
做我的儿子你后悔吗
I was taken aback at the time
我当时一愣
and I raised my eyes to see the family portrait.
我抬眼看到全家福
Grandparents spend their twilight years in peace.
爷爷奶奶安度晚年
My parents worked hand in hand for most of their lives.
父母携手过了大半辈子
All my family members
一家人整整齐齐
are safe and sound.
平平安安
No one answered the question
那天我们
that day.
谁也没有回答谁
But I'll never forget
但那天晚上
that night in my whole life.
我这辈子都不会忘记
We do not advocate
我们并不主张
sacrificing ourselves
在家庭发生冲突的时候
when the family conflicts.
去牺牲自己
But can we
但是能否
think more about the feelings of our family
当我们在处理人生这段
when we are dealing with
最重要的关系的时候
the most important relationship in life?
多去想想家人的感受
To understand
多去体会体会
their situation more
他们的处境
because one day
因为有一天
we
我们
will become them.
就成了他们
Thank you.
谢谢
What to eat? What to eat?
吃什么 吃什么
We must have
我们这次一定要
a delicious meal this time.
吃顿好吃的
If this continues like this
再这样下去
I don't know
我都不知道
whether I should hope you win
希望你们赢好
or not.
还是输好了
Ah.
哎
I'll follow you.
你吃什么我就吃什么
Hey,
哎呀
Stop your public display of affection.
你俩别再撒狗粮了
This is called a double harvest of career and love.
我这叫事业爱情双丰收
OK?
好吗
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Gong Chen
宫晨
Who is he?
他是谁啊
He was Xiaoyu's Prince Charming in the high school.
他是小鱼高中的男神